OKEMBO, CLIFFORD OTIENO

Address: C\o Kitengela East S.D.A Church,

Date of Birth: Feb 15, 1984 **Marital Status:** Married

Nationality: Kenyan Languages: English, Kiswahili

Sex: Male

OBJECTIVE

To be employed with an organization seeking an outstanding record in providing long term solutions for making the world a better place for man through geospatial technology.

SUMMARY OF QUALIFICATION

Highly self-motivated, energetic, creative and versatile individual with eight years of professional experience in delivering working solution using Geospatial technology in various industries. Interested in capacity building through education and training. Proficient in technical support on ArcGIS and ENVI products to professionals in various industries and applications. Strong leadership skills and great value to teamwork in achieving set goals and objectives. Interactive and can work with other professionals from different backgrounds and cultural beliefs. Love to the environment and its conservation or efforts to reduce its degradation. Care for the humanity and services geared towards improving livelihoods and living standards of people in adverse situations of calamities and disasters. Fast in learning new skills and in changing with technology.

EDUCATION

Oct, 2019 – Expected Oct, 2023: Doctor of Philosophy in People, Land and Urban Systems

ITC, University of Twente, Enschede, the Netherlands

Phone: +254723 525 944

Research: Development of a LADM based Kenyan cadastral data model

and Related Processes and Workflows

Jan, 2012 – Dec, 2012: Masters of Science in Geographic Information System

University of Redlands, Redlands, California, USA

Specialization: Project Management, GIS Database Management, GIS

Analysis, and Cartography

Jan, 2005 – Jun, 2008: Bachelor of Arts Geography

Moi University, Eldoret, Kenya

Specialization: GIS and Remote Sensing

Jan, 1999 – Dec, 2002: High School

Mavoko Secondary School, Athi-river, Kenya

Jan, 1991 - Dec, 1998: Primary School

Bar-Kawarinda Primary School, Kisumu, Kenya

CERTIFICATIONS & OTHER TRAINING

• PM-PFP-PRINCE2 Foundation Certification

- CompTIA CTT+: Classroom Instructor
- Esri Certified ArcGIS Desktop Associate
- Esri Certified Enterprise Geodatabase Management Associate
- Environmental Impact Assessment and Environmental Audit

WORK EXPERIENCE

Jan, 2018 to Present: Esri Eastern Africa

Senior Manager: Technical: Technical Department

Jan, 2019 to Present: Technical University of Kenya

Tutorial Fellow: Faculty of Applied Science and

Technology, School of Physical Sciences and Technology,

Department of Geo-Science and Environment

Sep, 2014 to Dec, 2018: Technical University of Kenya

Sessional Assistant Lecturer: Faculty of Engineering Science and Technology, School of Surveying and

Geospatial Sciences

Jan, 2014 to Dec, 2017: Esri Eastern Africa

Solutions Manager: Solutions Department

Jan, 2013 – Dec, 2013: Esri Eastern Africa

GIS Analyst: Training and Services Department

Jan, 2010 - Dec, 2011: Esri Eastern Africa

Instruction Coordinator: Training and Services Department

Jan, 2009 - Dec, 2009: Esri Eastern Africa

Marketing Executive: Sales and Marketing Department

Jul, 2008 - Dec, 2008: Esri Eastern Africa

Intern: Training and Services Department

May, 2007 – Jul, 2007: Ministry of Environment and Mineral Resources,

Department of Resource Surveys and Remote Sensing

Thtom: Remote Sensing CIS and Data Management

Intern: Remote Sensing, GIS and Data Management

Division

RESPONSIBILITIES

Senior Manager: Technical: Technical Department

Esri Eastern Africa

- Promotes the adoption of Geospatial solutions based on Esri's ArcGIS and partner Technologies to all industries.
- Leads the company is all its technical engagements for presale; proposals, system architecting needs assessments, system Audits, proposal writing and proof of concepts.

- Manage all the company's implementation, consulting project, training and Technical support
- Develop and manage the ICT maturity and systems

Sessional Assistant Lecturer: Faculty of Engineering Science and Technology, School of Surveying and Geospatial Sciences

Technical University of Kenya

- Teach both theory and practical, Assess and examine students on the following courses units:
 - o Database Management Systems
 - Geospatial Standards
 - o Computer Programming for GIS
 - o Geospatial Data Infrastructure
 - o Intelligent Transportation Systems and Management
 - o Geoinformation Systems: Basic and Advanced
 - o Project Management
 - o Geo-Positioning Systems
 - o GIS and Remote Sensing
 - GeoMarketing

Solutions Manager: Solutions Department

Esri Eastern Africa

- Identify, define, prioritize, schedule and assign key tasks and activities, and provide the required direction and resources to achieve the team's goals and objectives.
- Monitor and control the progress, scope and quality of the team's work, outcomes and deliverables, and take corrective action if and when needed.
- Develop the leadership qualities and professional competencies within the team through feedback, coaching sessions, training and performance reviews.
- Liaise with other members of the sales management team to make bid / no-bid, make or buy and partnering decisions for large sales opportunities.
- Coordinate and facilitate the timely development, review and submission of bid proposals in response to open tenders, EoIs, RfPs or validated business needs.
- Design, identify, and adapt suitable methodologies, tools and techniques for requirement analysis, use case modelling, and prototype development.
- Identify and prioritize prototype solutions on the basis of strategic value, repeatability and reusability, and oversee their development, documentation and dissemination.
- Manage the relationship with existing technology partners and match existing solutions with common user requirements to identify new partner solutions.
- Nurture upcoming talents through attachments and internships and also coordinate the internship/attachment program

GIS Analyst: Training and Services Department

Esri Eastern Africa

- Offer custom Geospatial solution to clients across industries and application
- Write and review technical proposals
- Lead ArcGIS and ENVI products' teams

- Teach GIS, GPS and Remote Sensing classes
- Develop and demonstrate prototype solution to clients

Instruction Coordinator: Training and Services Department **Esri Eastern Africa**

- Esri authorized instructor (ITP) for ArcGIS Foundation Courses, Building Geodatabases, Creating and Publishing Maps with ArcGIS courses
- Exelis VIS authorized instructor for ENVI Courses
- Course content development, localization and customization
- Learning Centre Administrator in-charge of all training programs and authorization
- A member of Brand Equity team dealing with corporate branding based on Esri guidelines

Marketing Executive: Sales and Marketing Department Esri Eastern Africa

• Overseer of all marketing activities, materials and events

Intern: Training and Services Department

Esri Eastern Africa

- Assist Technical support and development of solutions to users
- Learn about ArcGIS Desktop and ArcPad

Intern: Remote Sensing, GIS and Data Management Division **Departments of Resource Surveys and Remote Sensing**

- Part of the Land use/land cover and change detection project teams
- Assists in various field works, image preprocessing, on-screen digitizing and report compilation
- Learn about ArcView 3.2, Ilwis 3.4, Erdas IMAGINE 8.5

ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- **1. Geospatial Society of Kenya (GeoSK):** Formulated the GeoSK, now going through the registration process at the Registrar of Societies office and will officially launch soon. About 300 members on board and several activities planned.
- **2. Geospatial Information Standards:** Proposed the formulation of Geospatial Information Technical Committee to work on the Standard in the industry. Already accepted by KEBS and functional.

OTHER RESPONSIBILITIES

Nov, 2010 to present: Represents Esri Eastern Africa at the Information Technology for

Learning, Education and Training (ITLET), a technical

committee by Kenya Bureau of Standards (KEBS); a mirror of ISO TC 98, commissioned to come up with e-learning standards for

Kenya

Jan, 2017 to present: Represents Esri Eastern Africa at the **Geographic**

Information/Geomatics, a technical committee by Kenya Bureau of Standards (KEBS); a mirror of ISO TC 211, commissioned to come

up with geospatial information standards for Kenya

HANDS-ON SKILLS

Geographic Information System and Remote Sensing Software

- ArcGIS System of products
- ERDAS IMAGINE
- ENVI products
- TerraSync and Pathfinder Office

Statistical Software

• SPSS and other statistical packages

Spreadsheet and Database packages

- Microsoft Excel
- Microsoft Access

Presentation and Word Processing Package

- Microsoft PowerPoint
- Microsoft Word

E-mail

- Microsoft Outlook
- Browser based Gmail and yahoo mail

Programming Languages

- Python
- JavaScript
- HTML and CSS

AFFILIATIONS

- Society of Conservation GIS (SCGIS)
- Association of American Geographers (AAG)
- Geospatial Society of Kenya (Pioneer member and chairman)

SEMINARS & TRAININGS ATTENDED

August 11 - 29, 2008- Completed Environmental Impact Assessment and Environmental Audit Training at the School of Environmental Studies, Moi University, Eldoret.

October 5 - 9, 2007 – Completed the Existing GIS Users training at African institute for capacity development (AICAD), Nairobi, Organized and sponsored by Survey of Kenya and Japan International Cooperation (JICA).

July 23 - 24, 2007- Completed the **fast tracking with ArcGIS for Natural Resources** developed and presented by Juniper GIS Services, Inc organized by Society for Conservation GIS at the Regional Centre for Mapping of Resources for Development RCMRD, Nairobi.

July 18 - 20, 2007- Attended the Society for Conservation GIS first Annual conference on the **Geospatial Technology for Biodiversity Conservation and Management** at UNEP Headquarters Nairobi Kenya.

PUBLICATIONS AND PRESENTATIONS

December, 2012 - Master's project/thesis on the Web Maps for Environmental Learning at Highland Sam J. Racadio Library & Environmental Learning Center, City of Highland, California, USA. http://inspire.redlands.edu/gis_gradproj/161/

May, 2008 - Undergraduate dissertation on the Application of Remote Sensing and GIS in Assessing the Rainwater Harvesting Potential in Upper Nyakach Division, Nyando District, Kenya.

REFEREES

Dr. Ruijin Ma

Associate Professor for Geographic Information System University of Redlands 1200 East Colton Avenue P.O Box 3080 Redlands, California, 92373-0999, USA

Tel: +1 909 362 3250

Ruijin_ma@spatial.redlands.edu

Dr. Gilbert Nduru

Senior Lecturer and Head of Department - Karatina University Department of Geography P.O BOX 1957 - 10101 Karatina, KENYA

Tel: +254 729 328 787

Email: gilnduru@gmail.com

Prof. Gordon O. Wayumba

Director – School of Surveying and Geospatial Sciences Technical University of Kenya P.O Box 52428 – 00200 Nairobi, KENYA

Tel: +254 722 775 168

Email: gowayumba@gmail.com

Mr Patrick Chege

Executive Director Esri Eastern Africa P.O Box 58773 – 00200

Nairobi KENYA Tel: +1 909 213 8713

Email: pchege@esriea.com

(Operating from the US)